Thank you Amos. Hello everybody. Amos
that was a lovely tribute to Mike and
and so I won't say too much more other than to
say that I can't believe the firefighter problem
has come back into our workshop I think so many of
us remember the spirited debate that ensued when
that firefighter problem first  was introduced
and so much so that I think that we actually
had to declare a moratorium on discussions in
subsequent meetings because it kind of took
over our debate so it was lovely to to be
reminded of that happier time and that
happier moment I just want to say that
you know Amos mentioned Mike was a constant
in the activities of our institute and
just for me personally having him as a co-chair
on the advisory board made decision making
easier and and it was just a comfort
to know we were pursuing a shared vision and so
I too will miss him greatly and and there's a
large hole there that I'm not sure how we're
gonna fill moving on to the first session
and I don't I haven't seen whether carl is here
but I assume Karl is here somewhere and
and I can't tell from the zoom but but let's
assume that Karl is here our first speaker I'm
delighted to introduce is for our invited
session is Karl Fristen he's a theoretical
neuroscientist and an authority on brain imaging
he invented statistical parametric mapping
voxel-based morphe morphometry and
dynamic causal modeling these contributions
were motivated by schizophrenia research and
theoretical studies of value learning formulated
as the disconnection hypothesis of schizophrenia
his mathematical contributions include variational
laplacian procedures and generalized filtering
for hierarchical bayesian model inversion
he currently works on models of functional
integration in the human brain and the principles
that underlie neuronal interactions his main
contributions to theoretical neurobiology is a
free energy principle for action and perception
known as active inference his awards are way
too numerous to list here but one thing i
will note I asked him whether there was anything
he wanted me to add and he said I was free to do
that and and some of you know how dangerous that
can be but I will add that um that I noticed that
he's got and and this is as an economist this is
just massive he's got over 144 google scholars
like 144,000 google scholar citations  so
with without further ado and it
gives me great pleasure to introduce Karl Fristen
Karl take it away thank you very much that was one
indeed one of my favorite facts about me that you
that you picked up let me just
get myself organized and then
well again thank you for that lovely introduction
and it's a great pleasure and honor to to be
invited to speak to you and particularly on
this sort of sad occasion I'm intrigued by the
firefighter problem that's sounds
something I'd like to discuss even if you're not
allowed to discuss it I'm not sure I'm going to
get to that depth or problem or challenge
my hope was in the next 30 35 minutes
was to introduce a perspective on evidence
accumulation the handling of information from
the point of view of normative models of sentient
creatures, creatures like us or indeed viruses
and plants and I'm going to take my lead from a
simple assumption that every self-organizing
system every information processing system
is at the end of the day thinking and behaving
in a way to maximize the evidence for its models
of the world and I'm going to try and motivate
that from a sort of machine learning perspective
practically and as the talk goes on show how
these ideas translate in terms of the sentient
behavior of biotic systems like like
animals including ourselves as has been
mentioned this comes under the rubric in the life
sciences of as active inference active sensing
sensing in the spirit of trying to disclose
those data of that sensory information which
resolves the greatest amount of uncertainty about
your model or hypothesis about how those data were
caused now if we have time i'll give you a brief
simulation of the sort of epistemic foraging that
ensues from this so self-evidencing is very
simple all it's saying is you can account for
most perspectives on behavior in terms
of this single underlying imperative
which is that your internal states of the
processing system say internal brain states
and the way that you act upon the world the things
that you can control on the outside are both there
in order to maximize the probability of some
observables or outcomes given or conditioned upon
me or a model of how those outcomes were generated
and I'm just motivating the simplicity of
this assumption from the perspective of a
number of global approaches to behavior and
self-organization in the life and sometimes the
physical sciences so if these outcomes are the
most likely kind of outcomes that I would expect
to encounter then they define operationally
my characteristic outcomes to which I will aspire
and apparently work towards so in economics you
could think of the log of the probability of an
outcome given it is experienced or witnessed by
a particular model or me as standing in for
a value or a utility and from that one can spin
off reinforcement learning optimal control theory
and indeed in economics expected utility theory
that's interesting because the negative quantity
of this way of reading value is self-information
surprising or more simply surprised that means
that this imperative here the self-evidencing
simply translates as the imperatives to maximize
the mutual information for example the infamous
principle in neuroscience or the principles
of minimum redundancy maximum efficiency
from Horus Barlow and indeed the free energy
principle which we have been involved with where
this free energy serves as a bound on
this quantity and self-information here
that itself in turn is interesting because the
time average of self-information is entropy which
means that this imperative is self-evidencing
and can also be read as the holy grail of
self-organization many to minimize the dispersion
or the the entropy or the dissipation of my
observable states that you find in theories
of self-organization ranging from cybernetics
synergetics and of course if you're a physiologist
this is just a statement of homeostasis keeping
physiological states within viable bounds
but I'm going to take another perspective
on this quantity and treat this quantity as the
probability of some data given a generative model
where in basic statistics that would be called
the the bayesian model evidence or more
generally the marginal likelihood marginalized
marginalizing over all the parameters that
engendered or generated those data there
and in my world that leads to things like the
bayesian brain hypothesis formulations of
evidence accumulation predictive coding
in engineering and now indeed in the
neurosciences so I'm just going to now unpack
that kind of self-evidencing in a slightly more
technical way with a special emphasis on
this variational free energy that
serves in machine learning as a bound
on the log evidence in the sense that we can
create a variational bound simply by equipping
the log evidence with a quantity that can never
be less than zero namely a k-l divergence and in
this instance it's a k-l divergence between the
some approximate or bayesian beliefs about states
of the world generating the data and the true
posterior over those states if I were able
given those data so by optimizing extremizing
this free energy and we have on the one hand
a convergence of our beliefs encoded by our
internal states to the true posterior whilst
on the other hand this bound now becomes a
bound approximation to the log evidence that
this self-evidencing principle aspires
to maximize and just to motivate
why this might be a useful perspective and what
you get from this is essentially explainable
artificial intelligence in the sense that having a
generative model there commits you to writing down
a way in which your data were generated that
you can explain to somebody else it also
requires you to make explicit and transparent
your prior assumptions that are entailed
by the form and the structure of that generative
model and any hyper parameters associated with it
in a sense it also gives you a design
optimality in terms of
making optimal decisions of an objective sort in
terms of and using this model in order to make
inferences about the causes or the way that your
data were generated and that itself we will see
leads to a principled way for data mining or data
foraging and indeed epistemics and generalized
artificial general intelligence particularly
with sparse data we'll come to that but there
is another perspective though or another way of
carving up this variational free energy functional
and so just by rearranging the terms I can also
read it as a mixture of accuracy and complexity
so essentially the free energy is accuracy
minus the complexity where the complexity here
scores the difference between my bayesian beliefs
after seeing some data and my prior beliefs so
literally the degrees of freedom or the amount to
which I have changed my mind in the face of some
data and that complexity term plays an important
role in many guises is it's just an expression
of Occam's Principle in the brain it leads
to things like factorizations and functional
specializations a simpler way of explaining or
making sense of data with minimum redundancy and
maximum efficiency if you're an engineer it
also implies that you're aspiring to provide an
accurate account of observable data with the
minimum computational cost leading to notions
of bounded rationality literally based upon an
evidence bound known in my world as approximate
bayesian inference that rests upon priors that
sometimes people refer to as heuristics and of
course one can appeal now to the physics of
information by the Drazinski equality and
Landauer's principle which means that minimizing
computational cost also implies a thermodynamic
efficiency that in principle the best way of
accounting for data or making sense of data
should be that way that uses up the least energy
and is performed in the minimum amount of time
so the basic story I want to tell in this short
presentation rests upon thinking about well
that's fine for understanding sentient
behavior and a principle for sort of
optimal action in the moment what would it mean if
I considered devices artifacts or creatures that
can plan into the future and have a generative
model of the consequences of their action and
what would this self-evidence imperative mean
for plans and the kinds of behavior we'd expect
to see under that imperative and the answer
is or one answer at least is very simple
your because now I am trying to maximize
or optimize a free energy bound on evidence but
in the absence of actual outcomes the outcomes
become a random variable and I can simply take
the expectation of this evidence bound under
the predictive distribution of the outcomes that
would ensue if I did that and if we follow that
through what we're going to see is that basically
we can explain the best kinds of plans the
self-evidencing plans as fulfilling two
imperatives one that of bayesian optimal base
optimal design experimental design in terms of
maximizing expected accuracy whilst making bayes
optimal decisions by minimizing risk by minimizing
the expected complexity and I'm going to basically
rehearse the observational suggestion that
minimizing expected sorry maximizing expected free
energy is basically a mixture of these two things
just to make this a bit more heuristic what
I would normally do to your psychology audience
is ask them to imagine that they are an
owl and that you're hungry and then
I'd normally ask a member of the audience what
are you going to do I won't do that now but
I'm hoping that you're all thinking well I'm going
to go look for food indeed that is the absolutely
the correct answer but in answering like that
what you have said is something quite fundamental
and I'm going to try and unpack how important
that answer is just by comparing and contrasting
two ways of writing down normative or objective
functions for good behavior and I'm actually
going to repair these two perspectives you know
in a few slides but I'm going to deliberately sort
of introduce and celebrate this distinction
or this dialectic first of all I could assume
that if I make a move on the world I implement a
particular action you then there are going to be
certain states in the world that ensue and I may
have a value function over those states and if I
had a value function of states then there exists
a policy that is defined in terms of the best
action to take from any given state namely that
which maximizes the value of the ensuing state
however there is another way of formulating good
behavior which speaks to the answer I'm going to
look for food because looking and searching can
be construed as a way of minimizing uncertainty in
this instance where the prey is and uncertainty
is an attribute of a probability distribution
I'm going to refer that as a bayesian belief or a
conditional probability distribution so that tells
us something really important it says the best
behaviors the best actions the best plans are
cannot be functions of states of the world they
have to be functionals of beliefs about states
of the world and that answer looking for food
also tells you something else because it matters
whether I look for my prey and then I eat it or
whether I try to eat it and then look for my prey
so that introduces a notion of sequential
policies or sequential actions that have to be
optimized in relation to this functional of um
of beliefs about states of the world and I'm
going to frame that that aspect of optimizing
a trajectory or a sequence of plans in terms of
a principle of least action where action
here is just the path of the time integral of
a function of beliefs and indeed it's going
to be the expected free energy and hence the path
of the time integral of the free energy is an
action so what we have at hand here are two very
different ways of thinking about sort of a good
way to exchange with our world on the one hand
you've got bellman's optimality principle that
rests upon a value function of states and
many of you will be familiar with that in terms
of optimal control theory dynamic programming deep
reinforcement learning basic decision theory and
so on but there is another way of thinking about
it and that's possibly slightly simpler
appeals to hamilton's principle of stationary
action or at least action and that's really um
the principle that the free energy principle
inherits from  we'll also see that this is
very closely aligned with notions of artificial
curiosity and intrinsic motivation in robotics
the principles behind acquiring the right kind of
data optimal bayesian design and sequential
policy optimization so I'm just going to
take you through the functional form of this
objective function one more time because I think
you know its simplicity is compelling
and it speaks exactly to a variational or
an appeal to hamilton's principle at least action
as possibly another way of thinking about
behavior or at least sentient behavior so this
is the the basic setup that we use to understand
and simulate and indeed model behavior
and choices that are informed by observations
we have some observations that come in they
are used to optimize our bayesian beliefs about
hidden states of the world behind the observations
generating those observations and we do that by
finding the most accurate account that's as simple
as possible of those data and then we take those
beliefs about hidden states or latent states
of the world and then we use them to evaluate
the expected free energy given a particular
policy and in so doing we're effectively
taking the expected complexity and the expected
accuracy conditioned upon a way of moving forward
and that equips every way of moving forward
every policy with a score and expected free energy
that can be associated with a long probability
of me doing that and then I can just apply
a soft max operator find the most likely plan
select my next action change the outside world
that will generate new data and so the
cycle continues so that's the basic idea
is exactly the same equations that I've unpacked
as previously just to reiterate that we can
either regard this free energy function on
this evidence-bound excuse me as a mixture of
complexity and accuracy or we can just rearrange
it to express it as a bound on log evidence as you
do say in machine learning or deep learning with
things like variation auto encoders  and
the reason I've done it like that is just to see
what happens to these terms when we take the
expectation to form the expected free energy
and what happens is the complexity becomes a risk
the inaccuracy becomes ambiguity the evidence
bound becomes something uh known in um economics
and robotics as intrinsic value or motivation
and the log evidence becomes an extrinsic value
that we'll see in a moment can be associated with
things like expected utility so what licenses
my interpretation of these expected terms well
let me just go through and unpack this expected
free energy by looking at a number of different
special cases let's pretend that my prior beliefs
about outcomes given I am me encode my preferences
my prior preferences about the sort of outcomes
I expect to encounter following all actions and
let's assume I'm agnostic about what happens I
have no particular preferences for this of that
outcome that just leaves this quantity
here which is the expected evidence bound
and this quantity is just the mutual information
or expected mutual information between the causes
and the consequences under a particular
plan of soliciting those outcomes there
in neurobiology particularly in the visual
search literature where you people try to
work out where am I going to look next you know
what motivates that visual palpation of the world
the motivation is just the intrinsic value of
resolving uncertainty called bayesian surprise
more I think revealingly is just the
degree of belief updating or information gain
afforded some outcomes in other words the
difference not the k-l divergence between
my bayesian beliefs about hidden states if
I were able to see the outcomes that ensued
following a policy compared to my beliefs before
looking at those outcomes again speaking to the
difference between a posterior and a prior but now
in the future so it's an expected divergence or
belief updating or information gain that is
intrinsically valuable irrespective of what you
think or will prefer to happen let me now
take another source of uncertainty off the table
namely the ambiguity I'm going to
make a simplifying assumption that
I can see all the hidden states of the world
that my sensations my sensory observables
are a direct mapping of the states of the world
that generated them and in this instance
the s's become the o's and we're
only left this ambiguity term disappears
and we're just left with this quantity here which
is another k-l divergence or relative entropy here
namely the difference between my anticipated
outcomes or states given a particular policy
and my preferred outcomes my prior preferences
so all we're saying here is that the
actions that have the optimal expected free energy
are just those in the absence of any ambiguity
that minimize risk as scored by the difference
between what I anticipate will happen and what a
priori I prefer to happen and if I make a final
move which is to take the last kind of uncertainty
out of the game namely the uncertainty that
depends about states the world that depends
upon my action that I'm just left with this term
here the extrinsic value but if you remember we're
associating with utility in economics or negative
loss functions in optimal control theory which
just means we're trying to optimize the expected
long probability of our preferred outcomes or
expected value here so what we have at hand
is a decomposition that applies to policies
when scored in terms of an expected free energy
functional and that can be unpacked or carved
into an expected value that underwrites these
optimal decisions but importantly this epistemic
term this information gain that is informally
identical to the principles that underlie bayes
optional design and things like active learning
with unknown parameters so in short the expected
value plus the information gain is literally equal
to the expected free energy I slipped this slide
in because I thought some of you might like to
think of it in terms of information diagrams
but given the time constraints um and the
opportunity for discussion I'm not going
to go into that it's just an interesting game
that you can play in terms of thinking about
an information theoretic partition in terms of um
basing design information bottlenecks empowerment
another takes on the right kinds of information
gathering behavior I want to whip through
now a simulation because you know we want
to leave as much time for any discussion
that sort of exemplifies how these mechanics
would unfold in empirical behavior in my world
here looking at sort of small animals or rats
making decisions what we normally do is build
a generator model based upon a markov decision
process of discrete states that generate outcomes
parameterized by a likelihood of mapping a and
then we make the transitions over time among the
hidden states depend upon some policy depending
upon property transition matrices where the policy
itself rests upon my pride preferences or some
cost function and then I can equip this model with
a few initial priors and hyper parameters I have
now got a completely a fairly complete description
of any kind of behavior that can be written down
in terms of discrete updates of hidden or latent
states that generate observables I can then apply
standard variational techniques to optimize my
variational and expected free energies
essentially using off the shelf technology
that rests upon defining this approximate
posterior just from really from my interest
when one takes these off the shelf belief updating
basic belief updating variational message passing
or belief propagation schemes they look remarkably
similar to the way that neuroscientists understand
message passing and belief updating the in the
brain in terms of perceptions updating beliefs
about expected states of the world policy
selection usually associated with the
striatum or integration between parts of the
surface of the brain and the striatum that
rests upon this expected free energy and indeed
some hyperplasia or hyper precision parameters
reflecting the confidence or the uncertainty
that I afford my beliefs about what I'm going
to do next we can do learning and then we just
select the action on the basis of these updated
expectations about policies so when we do that
and I'll just close with an example of a synthetic
rat doing this so this little paradigm here
involves a rat in a tea maze it can go and secure
a reward that's either on the right or the left
of the two upper arms it could only make two moves
but it's got the opportunity to go to the
lower arm and get an instructional cue that
tells it that the cue is the the war reward is on
on the left or on the right hand side so it's got
a choice it can either take a gamble and go to the
one of the two upper arms and be right or wrong
and it has to stay there so these are absorbing
states when it gets to the baited areas or it can
waste one of its moves by finding out exactly
where the reward is and then go and secure its
reward with a high degree of uncertainty so from
the point of view of expected utility these are
fairly balanced options but clearly from the point
of view of this self-evidencing in the future
the information gain the intrinsic value of
going to resolve your uncertainty or this rats
uncertainty about the states of affairs is
going to be more attractive and that's going to
compel the rat to be exploratory and go
and look at the cue get that and then go and
get its reward and and indeed that is what
it does i'm just summarizing the behavior that
follows from integrating those belief
propagation or variational message passing
schemes under this charity model but with a
twist after the first couple of trials we leave
the reward here so that in principle the rat is
going to start to learn that the reward is always
here and indeed it does that and of course as it
becomes more and more confident that the reward is
here the intrinsic value the epistemic value the
information gain afforded by going down here gets
smaller and smaller and smaller and wanes and once
it passes a threshold where the expected utility
of going straight to the reward and staying
there for an extra move and supervenes then
its behavior switches deterministically
and it switches from an exploration
to an exploitation mode and that's exactly what
happens in this example after about the 20th
20th trial here and all this depends upon
accumulating knowledge about the contingencies
namely the context where on which side is the
reward most likely to be over successive exposures
that then couples back into this online
active influence planning as inference
underwritten by this expected free energy this
is the last slide I'm putting in this in just
to remind myself that there's an
outstanding challenge here I've sort of um
sold this self-evidencing as a
something that has constructed into in relation
to lots of other ways of describing good behavior
there may be a deeper backstory to this that
relates to statistical physics and things like the
integral fluctuation theorem but to connect or
complete that story it requires one small move
which I'm happy to talk about um
but not happy to waste any more time
unpacking for you at the moment so i'll give the
last word to Einstein that everything should be
made as simple as possible but not simpler so it
just reminds me for me to thank those people whose
ideas I've been talking about and of course thank
you for your attention thank you very much indeed
terrific Karl thank you thank you so much
for that really engaging talk and a great
way to start off our our workshop
I realized I actually forgot to to mention
to everybody else who's here that that what
the format was going to be so we did actually
plan for some ample time for questions
and for discussion I think as we know as people
who have been to our workshops before know that's
one of the hallmarks of our workshops is a quite
animated discussion and so thank you Karl
also for leaving ample time for that so I want to
open the floor up to discussions and questions
maybe if you want to just drop a note into the
chat to me just to tell me of a question
so that we can organize or line up the
questions but I think the first question i
know almost has a few questions so we'll
go to Amos first but just drop me a note as i
said if you have questions to ask thank you Karl
first it's nice to see you again I
really enjoyed your talk and and the idea that
you were able in such a simple way to put
decision theory within information theoretic
framework in quantities mostly the k-l
divergence seem to be very interesting very nice i
myself even though I work on this area
for many years I never really saw it in
in this way so thank you for this I have a
a simple question though it could be outside
the scope here in a previous time I've seen
you were talking about marco blanket and
as as you were passing saw in one of the slides
I saw that you put your framework within a Markov
blanket maybe I missed it and it may be outside
what you wanted to talk today but if it's not I
would be happy to hear a little bit more how this
fits within your theory of Markov blanket
that's a very astute question yes I tried to
slip past the Markov blanket because it would
take another half hour to motivate that but that's
an excellent question because it speaks to that
last slide where it were once trying to find
a deeper backstory in statistical physics to
why this kind of self-evidence behavior has to be
there if any system manages to maintain itself
in some kind of steady state you know if it's in
computational chemistry this will be self-assembly
if it's in biology it be autopoiesis if it's
in social neurosciences it's just basically
maintaining cohesions and and in groups and
and that's where the markov blanket comes in so
in order to talk about a system you'd have to
actually write down well what do you mean by
a system that has some states how are those states
differentiated from the states that do not belong
to the system so that implies a set of conditional
independences that as you've noted um
are usually assigned to the blanket states the
markov blanket so what you say is well in order
to differentiate a system from the rest of
the universe I will assume the existence
of some states that when I condition the internal
states on they become conditionally independent
of the external states and those are the blanket
states and then you look at the the density
dynamics that you have under that particular
partition of states into inside and outside
separated by blanket states that still permit
so the system's still open because you can
the outside can vicariously influence the
inside and vice versa through the blanket states
but you then look at the the statistical
physics of that partition and that's where
the integral fluctuation theorem kicks in which
is why I  was trying to and I'm still trying to
connect the optimum bayesian design plus optimum
bayesian decision theory formulation in terms of
information theory and k-l divergences with the
the k-l divergences underwrite the integral
fluctuation theorems so that's I think I
mean it's a little bit indulgent but I you know
it really does if you like join the
dots between the statistical physics
and the more practical aspects of
information gathering and exploitation
thank you great thank you Amos I think
our next question is from Bill Lawless
I know Bill you you put it in the chat but go
ahead and and unmute yourself and just ask it
thanks for reminding me to unmute I
it was really nice talk I liked it a lot
it seems to me to be based on the
information that's available or that could become
available and that leads me to my question it
seems that the only way that you can uncover
something like deception is when it uncovers
itself maybe you could address that but
I'd also like to find the link between which I
like bays and maximum entropy production maybe you
could also address that as well if you have time
yes we don't have time to address it properly
but we can certainly celebrate the existence of
those those important issues and questions and the
yeah the maximum entropy principle both as it
pertains in you know in the sort of classical
jamesian sense but also as it pertains to
entropy production in this sort of dynamic
self-assembly formulation in terms of the
integral fluctuation theorems and markov blankets
plays an incredibly important role and just you
know almost emerges from for free from the from
the free energy formulas so if you just
decompose the complexity you've basically got
the entropy of your beliefs about the causes of
the data and that has to be maximized as as
mandated by things like Occam's principle so
that's part of this sort of optimum-basing
design formulation and you know has its
roots in sort of jeffrey's priors and james's
interpretation of fiscal physics and that so
that is really at the heart of this um
belief based or at least conditional probability
distribution or bayesian belief based formulation
of optimal behavior the deception
issue is fascinating because it speaks to
the rather delicate and challenging and
very real issue of applying this mechanics to
dyadic or multi-agent games where now you
have the potential of the generative model
that sort of in this instance that markov decision
process being a model of another model so somebody
that I am in exchange with in a game theoretical
in a sort of language sense and just you
know the very notion of trust and deception
or indeed just the very notion of a generative
model being able to explain outcomes generated
by another generative model you know is deeply
challenging and we're talking about you know
sort of metacognition through to theory of mind
here so I think just things like deception and
regret are if you like the you know the most
challenging kinds of information exchange or
the most challenging aspects of exchange data
exchange that you would aspire to try
and explain in terms of your bayesian optimality
principles in this framework I'm not sure it's
been done yet there have been baby steps in terms
of putting these sort of free energy minimizing
agents together and what tends to happen is
that they tend to cooperate because they
want to make themselves mutually predictable
so if you're trying to minimize the
surprisal or the self-information
one way of doing that is just to make sure
that I am as much like you as possible under
the prior assumption that you are doing the
same and then our entire exchange becomes as
mutually as predictable as possible and that
and that optimizes then the joint free energy that
that we share did you have anything
deeper in terms of deception because
my answer is a little bit superficial in
the sense that it hasn't quite been done yet
yes I do but you mentioned the word
assembly which I find to be even more intriguing
one of the issues that I have with von
neumann's assembly idea is that there's
no way to tell when the correct pieces from von
neumann's model I don't know if that's what you're
addressing there's no way to know that the assembly
is working in the right direction that you're
actually improving the situation with assembly
maybe you could address that not in a scholarly
way because I don't know the the you know the
notion of assembly in the von neumann sense
so that's I'll have to put on the list with the
firefighter problem just to go google afterwards
simply in any sense how do you know that
you're assembling a team based on what you've said
you want to assemble it so that the surprise is
minimized so one way of addressing that
is well certainly through numerical analyses
and that's been done in the context of
dalic interactions but also an interesting
dance between the environment and a phenotype
or an assembly or ensemble of phenotypes in the
context of economic construction and the bottom
line is that the because the this variation
free energy is an extensive quantity
you can read the goodness of the assembly
or the ensemble of systems as simply the
sum of each individual's free energy so if
every individual of an assembled ensemble
is optimizing its free energy then collectively
that is also true and then that sort of brings
us back to what I was saying before that you know
that very much means that everybody's trying to
learn about each other so that they can render
everything else or indeed the environment as
predictable as possible so we build traffic
lights and roads and we have languages and
signs and deontic cues or I learn your language
while you learn mine so that that's sort of the
first order emergent property of this kind of
multi-agent assembly if that's what you meant
but I do note of course that doesn't leave any
room for deception so now you have to think about
in groups and out groups assemblies of this kind
versus that kind and how you might actually
use deception to exploit this sort of
first order cooperative mutual predictability
imperative that comes out of
self-evidencing with other things like me
I have a somewhat maybe it's related question
but so as as you were presenting I was I was
jotting down a note I made to myself and this is
related to things that I'm interested in about
the relationship so as an economist I'm
quite interested in people's perceptions and how
sometimes you know when we observe behavior
that we would often characterize as not rational
it actually is probably behavior that
is rational conditional on a set of
of beliefs that are possibly not correct
or perception that's possibly not correct
and so I was wondering about the distinction
between perception and what I would call
something like learned experience and your
slide on functional anatomy and message passing
seemed to discuss that and you seem to emphasize
that beliefs are about uncertainty and so I was
wondering if there was anything that incorporates
uncertainty associated with the learning side so
there's some uncertainty related to the outcome
the results from repeatedly doing the same thing
so you know and I think of in a rat experiment
you can design it so that there's a constancy of
the experience so that after 20 times the rat
knows where the food's going to be but and
presumably you can design a rat experiment where
there's some uncertainty as to whether the food
will be there but I was wondering about that
about how experience how you think about
learned experience and and how an individual
knows whether it's their perception
or whether it's actually a series of of
of experiences or you know basically there's
there's a dependence in there that I wasn't
clear how to incorporate into your models
right no excellent question and that
dependence is a really important part of
approximate bayesian inference that rests upon
a mean field approximation or a factorization of
beliefs about different kinds of things that when
you actually do the belief updating necessarily
it you know repairs that dependency so that
depends is absolutely crucial and central to any
realization of this obviously this amazing
belief updating and in particular beliefs about
sort of time invariant parameters of a generative
model that encode laws and contingencies
versus quickly changing states in the moment so
normally we talk about inferences basically belief
updating about latent states of the world while
learning is a slower updating of the parameters
of a generative model but you you bring up so
many intriguing issues and I just want to mention
a couple of bounded rationalities seems to me
semantically and possibly rather cheekily easily
absorbed into the use of an evidence bound to move
from exact basic inference to bounded bayesian
inference which sounds to me exactly like sort
of bounded rational and you could even chase up
further with the complete class theorems though
as you say for any given pair of loss functions
and behaviors there is a set of prior beliefs
that render that behavior renders that behavior
Bayes optimal so there's a lovely duality there
that all rests upon the prize that define
the generative model so that's that I think
that's a really important point that you
know we're all different because we're different
priors but we're all optimal well at least
give them those priors practically you also
brought the so the inference in learning
are both in the service of minimizing this
path integral of free energy that
in an identical way that when
you unpack the equations analytically
you get the sort of fast belief
updating that our neurons might do
for the inference part then you get this slow
accumulation of evidence and belief updating on
connectivity that underwrites the parameters
and when you start to do numerical analyses
something really simple but I think very telling
happens that if you set off your I'm sorry I
should say that in practice what we generally do
with discrete state space models is parameterize
the likelihood mappings and the prior
usually transition matrices in terms
of dirichlet parameters so you have to
write down your initial dirichlet accounts
now if you write them down very very small the
artifact then becomes very sensitive to evidence
so that you know if you start off with
your two outcomes and you've got one
dirichlet parameter after just one experience
one's going to be sort of twice the other
on the other hand if you start off with 200
dirichlet accounts and you add one more
you've got a ratio of 201 to 200 nothing
has really changed so your prior beliefs
encode an uncertainty about your beliefs
about the contingencies that you're learning
so if you come in as a sort of young artifact
that's just been born with very low divisional
accounts it'll be very sensitive to any evidence
that is accumulated through repeated exposure but
if you're an old wise recalcitrant rat you're not
going to learn anything and then it's interesting
when you come back to the previous discussion
you know when you put two of these agents together
they're trying to predict each other if you
put the old one with lots of dirichlet accounts
and interacting with the baby one with very small
dirichlet accounts then the small one learns a lot
more from the old one so it's a nice metaphor
for you know for teachers and parents and like
sorry that's quite interesting I mean I can
imagine a situation though where there's I mean
in some ways that that you know young one and how
it acquires experience is in some ways I think of
as an initial condition but over time you can
imagine something where there's like you know some
limited memory or memory decay so that in
some steady state there's you know it's not
the marginal additional piece of
information has the same effect on all the
different agents now I don't want to take up all
the time though because I know Duncan Foley also
has a question so I'm going to hand it over to
Duncan Foley as well for his question well thank
you for your presentation I'm particularly
intrigued by the ability of your ability
to bring out the parallels to the thermodynamic
concepts in this way of partitioning the
free energy relationships that are implicit
in the entropy reasoning I wanted to go just
get your thinking on a slightly different
topic which is what I would call novelty
because I'm aware that in
some models of learning an
important role is played by the ability of the
system to create new categories or new states or
not just to update in the typical bayesian
way but to innovate in some way or to accommodate
novelty and often there's a trade-off between
the organism's willingness to view something as
a novelty and start treating it as something
different we're trying to accommodate it
within the framework that's already been
established by experience I just wondered how
what your thinking is on how that relates to this
general perspective of bayesian updating learning
I think it relates intimately and actually
provides a sort of super ordinary context and
interestingly actually speaks to Robin's last
question which I would sort of frame in terms
of the problem with structure learning and
when do you build an extra bit of your model
to account for this new piece of data or indeed
remember there's also this imperative to keep
the model as simple as possible so yes you have
to have the optimal forgetting you have to have
the loss of redundant connections you have to you
have to forget stuff so it introduces this really
delicate issue when is it optimal to believe
update or indeed change the structure say the new
number of hierarchical levels in a deep network
or add another level to some hidden
factor so from the point of view of optimizing
the free energy bound on model evidence
this just is basic model selection so
structure learning just is basic model
selection under some prior beliefs about the
volatility of the environment and there will be
an answer to your question should I add an extra
level of say hierarchical depth to my model or not
in light of these data so you know if you
had all the time in the world then what you
would do is you'd basically evaluate the
marginal likelihood or the evidence bound
with and without that extra level and if the
evidence the marginal likelihood increased you
retain that extra level and if it decreased
then you would you lose the extra
level and I frame it like that because
there are some people who think that's
why we go to sleep that we rehearse all the data
that we've accumulated during the day and
effectively whilst doing things like dreaming
evaluate its capacity to explain those kinds
of data and then identify those
redundant parts of the model structure
and remove those connections and simplify and do
housekeeping of a structural sort so again it's
speaking to this sort of optimal forgetting that
Robin was alluding to and I suspect you know
the thrust of your question which is which is you
know when do I update when I don't update that
would be one part another really important part
of your question there was a notion of novelty
and novelty emerges and in this scheme in a
very simple way it's simply the information
gain or that intrinsic value not about hidden
states of the world but about the parameters
that we've just been talking about so if in
my evaluation of the expected free
energy of a particular move say looking over there
for example or doing this or opening that door
there is certainly an information gain an
epistemic value or affordance relating to
the resolution of uncertainty about what's behind
the door but there's also an epistemic value or
intrinsic value in terms of what would happen
if I do that generally and that's basically scored
by the k-l divergence between the posterior beliefs
encoded in by those dirichlet parameters or the
likelihood mappings or the priors before and
after making making that move it's actually very
very simple to evaluate so that you've now got
sort of two kinds of information intrinsic value
you've got the kind that scores the reduction
of uncertainty the information gain attributable
to bayesian beliefs over hidden states and the
other flavor which we can refer to say salience
and the other kind that has mathematically
exactly the same form but it's a reduction a
relative entropy or a reduction of uncertainty of
beliefs about parameters that you can think of as
novelty so that hasn't been explored very
much but it becomes absolutely crucial
when you start to try and explain
sort of higher end executive functions
in cognitive neuroscience like things
like sort of aha moments or insights
that require you to go and learn something about
the causal structure the regularities that endure
over multiple instances of a particular trial or a
particular self-sensory experience so in my world
in the active inference world that
is starting to attract a lot of
young people in terms of how they might simulate
and write that down thank you
great now I noticed Kendrick Nelson posted uh
something in the chat Kendrick do you want to
do you want to mention it or is it
fine that it's just in the chat it's not really
a question I can just explain it a little bit and
then if there's interest people can follow up but
you know as people are asking questions about
how you model deception and degrees of belief
in updating data one of the things that came
to mind is there's some really interesting work
by Fleming Topsoi who looks at these
information theoretic models and
games game theory and complexity and he uses
generalized entropies to model your willingness to
update your beliefs and particularly you can
parameterize it where the control parameter
becomes a your kind of perception of
risk or your perception of complexity
and then you can have different players react
differently to you know information games
where one player might you know just accept
reality and thereby you know when they get
new data they just accept that data
and update whereas another player
might be skeptical about reality and and
be less willing to change their beliefs
so it's a way of modifying these models to
account for biases and how people accept or reject
data and I think very important if you take these
ideas into the clinical realm in terms of
psych psychopathology and psychiatry you know
they're thinking about things like delusions
and illustrations or agnosias where people
have very different interpretations about what's
causing their sensations and afford very different
weights to the sense of evidence at hand versus
their pride beliefs so I think that's a
really important perspective just technically I
don't know this formulation but it sounds as if
you would reproduce that that mechanics by hyper
parameterizing the precision of various beliefs
so you know if you want to make a rat more
exploitative as opposed to explorative you
can certainly increase the precision of its prior
preferences so that it's the kind of rat that
very definitively likes these kinds of outcomes as
opposed to those kinds of outcomes and there's a
similar way you can you can parameterize
the precision of likelihood mapping so
if a likelihood mapping is very imprecise you're
going to ignore a lot of data because you know
that the predictability of that data or its
decision is low but on the other hand if you
assign your likelihood mappings undue precision
you will be enslaved and your belief updating
will be very susceptible to any data and you may
well start to overfit that data in relation to
your prior beliefs so I don't know but it sounds
as if that's the
set of questions about you know the relative
weighting of different sources of information
and the advantage of waiting of sensory likelihood
you know versions of prying priors that are being
addressed I'll just reiterate that sounds that
sounds important because it's in computational
psychiatry that is usually the seat of pathology
that explains a lot of false inference and
updating and in psychiatric conditions yeah
yeah right so everybody I think it's time
especially I'm cognizant of the fact that
in this virtual world we have to keep on
schedule so i'm going to close this here but
I just want to first of all I want to thank
Karl for for an excellent presentation I want to
thank everybody else for the great discussion and
and just like in a regular you know sort of
real world or in-person conference I mean Bill's
already posted a follow-up comment that I think
you know hopefully that I find very interesting so
hopefully we can take that into the break we
can continue this discussion on the break but
I just want to close the session now so there's
people who think 10 minutes and do whatever
they can do that but again thank you so much
Karl and and hopefully we can continue to have
discussions into the break thanks very
much Karl if you're still there I think
Bill had an interesting question and that that it
might be worth the having some discussion about
right sorry yes I was just
about to get a cup of coffee so
I'm sorry no coffee for
presenters I'm sorry about that
yeah this is the quantum biology quantum
models of biology wait Bill just Bill just
ask your follow-up question yeah it's the owl
problem now the owl waits for prey to
uncover itself but owls are also built in with
the intelligence that prey hide so it's got to go
into the business of uncovering a deception
volkswagen had an extraordinary deception
how do we uncover these deceptions ahead
of time that's the question I see that reminds
me the stag hunt paradigm have you do this is
cooperation versus competition in terms of
yeah and you know I don't have an informed
answer other than to say that you know this
is sort of high-end generative modeling
in either a game theoretic or game theory
sense or in a social neuroscience sense
and the trick is to build the sophistication
of the generative models so that they can
entertain or represent the possibility that
the other agent knows about the you know their
intentions and that requires quite sophisticated
quite sophisticated generative models and
then one gets I presume into the same realm of
sophistication that is found in economics
you know you to what extent do I represent your
representations of me and then to what extent do I
represent your representations of you representing
me representing you yeah I want level of
recursion does you know do you find that
sort of that optimum in terms of this sort of
bounce between the accuracy and the complexity
I don't know of any formal work
within the sort um the active inference scheme
but I do know that there's a chap called
john danizo who has looked at
evolutionary stable strategies in using sort
of levels of recursions of beliefs in terms of
dyadic interactions and actually found something
quite quite it wasn't quite so much the
prey camouflaging or deceiving the predator but
it was more about sort of populations
of two different kinds finding that evolutionary
stable strategy as quantified by a minimum or an
optimum expected free energy and what he found was
that the evolutionary stable strategy was half
the people had to be very unsophisticated and the
other half had to be very sophisticated and that
was the only stable strategy otherwise you
got this sort of leapfrogging where you
know the deceivers try to deceive the deceivers
deceiving the deceivers but there was a stable
strategy where there were basically sophisticated
non-sophisticated agents out there I'm not
sure it's framed in terms of deception though i
think this is more just in terms of communication
well thanks for your answer I'm
sorry to have interrupted your coffee
right I'll go so I've got to do deception fire
fighter problems and what was the other thing oh
yes the the von neumann assembly these are
things I have to go and do my homework on